<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="balisage-proceedings-html.xsl"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="../../../../Documents/Balisage/lib/balisage-author.css" title="Forms interface" alternate="no"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../../Documents/Balisage/lib/balisage-1-3.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0-subset Balisage-1.3"
  xml:id="HR-23632987-8973" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <title>Fractal is Information</title>
  <info>
    <abstract><para>What are markup languages aiming to achieve? A more precise wording of the question is what
        are we trying to achieve with markup languages. Mostly when we pose it, we are content with
        very local and specific answers: <quote>I am using XML [not JSON] because ...</quote>. To
        pose it more generally might seem perilous, as it quickly takes us to the outer reaches of
        philosophical abstraction, but one paraphrase of one answer might be, <quote>to help me cope
          with the chaos</quote>.</para>
      <para>This paper proposes that here, there is self-similarity across scales.</para></abstract>
    <author>
      <personname>
        <firstname>Wendell</firstname><surname>Piez</surname>
      </personname>
      <personblurb>
        <para>Wendell Piez is an independent consultant specializing in XML and XSLT, based in
          Rockville MD.</para>
      </personblurb>
    </author>
    
  </info>
  <section>
    <title>Information is fractal</title>
    <para>Let's postpone for a moment the question of whether to consider <quote>fractal</quote>
      here in its literal, or in a merely analogical sense. (That is, the phenomena we witness and
      register are like fractals, or fractal-like.) What are fractals like?</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Self-similarity across scales</para>
        <para>Disparate parts are similar (<quote>alike</quote>) but also different</para>
        <para>Boundaries become <quote>shaggy</quote> whenever we zoom in</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>There are rules, and there are also exceptions to the rules</para>
        <para>Another way to put it: regular, but also irregular</para>
        <para>Regularity punctuated by irregularities that may have their own (higher-level)
          regularity</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Scales of resolution</title>
    <para>Examples can be given</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Cultural production</para>
        <para>The archive!</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><quote>Documentary</quote> production (or: <quote>the written word</quote>)</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Electronic/documentary media</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Non-proprietary, open, standards-based media</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Text-based formats</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Formalisms, formal languages, programming languages</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Markup languages and data description syntaxes</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>The archetypal pattern?</title>
    <para>The box or envelope, with a label</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Semantic staircase: the example of plain text</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="order-chaos.svg"/>
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
        <para>A <quote>slope of optimization</quote>, as described in 2012</para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="notations-at-large.svg"/>
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
        <para>Rendered as a <quote>staircase</quote> with some more examples projected onto it
          (2018)</para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
    <para>We call it <quote>plain text</quote> because we mean to distinguish it with
        <quote>formatted text</quote>, at least as it presupposes that the <quote>format</quote> of
      text is something other than text itself, moreover not represented directly by it (<quote>not
        in Unicode</quote>) and thus to be expressed as more text, except now not text but the
      text-that-is-not-a-text. The irony and arbitrariness of this will be left for another paper.
      Nonetheless it is worth remarking how commonplace and ordinary it eventually seems that we can
      so easily
      distinguish:<programlisting>This is a text</programlisting>from<programlisting>{\*\ftnsep\chftnsep}\pgndec\pard\plain \s0\widctlpar\hyphpar0\cf0\kerning1\dbch\af5\langfe2052\dbch\af6\afs24\alang1081\loch\f3\fs24\lang1033{\rtlch \ltrch\loch
This is a text}
\par }</programlisting></para>
    <para>Many readers will recognize the second of these as <quote>This is a text</quote> embedded
      in a (piece of) an RTF document. (This is lines 15-17 of a 17-line file for this line of
      writing.) They, however, as they know, are exceptions: most people seeing this (even most
      readers) may not know that this is RTF. They do, however – indeed, demonstrating a
      sophisticated kind of pattern matching, can readily separate the text from the encoding. They
      might agree that the text is not quite <quote>plain</quote> subject to some definition of that
      term.</para>
    <para>And this comes up despite (what is also paradoxical) how <emphasis>both</emphasis>
      examples above are plain text, as distinguished from some other sort of encoded information
      (which would not, indeed, submit readily to transcription here).</para>
    <para>So for these purposes let us define plain text as <quote>an arbitrary but finite sequence
        (string) of Unicode characters</quote> (or of an analogous abstraction we can call a
        <quote>character</quote>) - fully aware that this is both too broad and too narrow. But it
      is a place to start, with the understanding that there will be edge cases.</para>
    <para>Among sorts of varieties of applications of plain text include what we might call
        <quote>raw</quote> - that is, without markup or inline encoding of any sort, through a
      spectrum up through rather complex organizations optimized for certain kinds of processing,
      data mining, and execution. One might indeed draw a map showing the <quote>tradeoff
        space</quote> between different approaches to plain text, with two axes representing (a)
      readily accessible processibility (that is, the explicit, overt and ready capabilities of the
      text for automated data processing operations), vs (b) the necessary up front commitment in
      the form of constraints over the text - that is, the rules of its use, including the use of
      embedded encodings, invocations of spirits and powers, and all sorts of magical incantations.
      For these to be operational and effective, they have to be done right.</para>
    <para>This can be called a staircase because what is important here is not the slope, or whether
      the slope is curved, or indeed whether two dimensions is adequate to the problem, but rather
      the incremental nature of the sorts of commitments that can be made. Note that since each step
      represents a new commitment, it entails a <emphasis>narrowing</emphasis>: an achievement of
      expressive power in one domain, at the cost of expression in others.</para>
    <para/>
    <para/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Bottom / no bottom</title>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Who doesn't want their own bespoke syntax?</title>
    <para>Especially if they can help design it</para>
    <para>(Everyone loves a hobby horse!)</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>All language is an early optimization</title>
    <para>Master the thing by representing it</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Meanwhile, the real world</title>
    <para>We haven't got it completely figured out yet.</para>
    <para>Check back later.</para>
  </section>
     
</article>
